<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-01T13:20:11+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Phono Phönix</title><subtitle>DJ and Hi-Fi Audio Electronics From Inside</subtitle><author><name>Ilia Frolov</name></author><entry><title type="html">Spicing Up The Turntable</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/spicing-up-the-turntable" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spicing Up The Turntable" /><published>2025-03-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/spicing-up-the-turntable</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/spicing-up-the-turntable"><![CDATA[<p>I found this topic both broad and fascinating when I was restoring my first pair of Technics. Many of these devices are now around 30 years old and have never been serviced in their lifetime. They are often full of dust, dirt, and sometimes even remnants of alcohol and party glitter. The height adjustment rings can get stuck, and the pitch faders can become rusted and scratchy. All of these issues require proper cleaning, re-greasing, and re-oiling. And of course, selecting the right materials is always a challenge.</p>

<p>While you can still find original grease or oil on eBay, I think it makes little sense to buy an overpriced tube of “original” grease for ten times the price of a good modern alternative. The market today offers better options that will last longer and provide the same original touch and feel for the moving parts.</p>

<p>Short disclaimer: I’m not affiliated with any of the companies whose products are mentioned here; I’m simply sharing my personal experience and the best tools I’ve found for my own use.</p>

<div class="blogPostImage">
<img src="/assets/posts/spicing-up-the-turntable/materials.jpeg" alt="Technical sprays, grease and oil" />
<div class="blogPostImageTitle">Technical sprays, grease and oil</div>
</div>

<h1 id="de-dusting">De-dusting</h1>
<p><strong>Kontakt 67</strong> is a compressed air spray for electronics which is perfect for tonearm detailing, especially in areas that are hard to reach with a cotton swab. It also removes dust from a PCB in seconds. However, I find the 30€ price tag quite steep for a 200ml bottle, even though it performs better than the more affordable Kontakt PB alternative.</p>

<h1 id="de-greasing">De-greasing</h1>
<p>There are plenty of options on the market, but the classic <strong>WD-40</strong> works just as well. It’s easy to find everywhere and evaporates quickly. Many people think of WD-40 as a lubricant, but it’s actually a solvent that helps remove old grease and loosen rusted parts. Always apply the proper grease after cleaning with WD-40.</p>

<h1 id="grease">Grease</h1>
<p><strong>Super Lube Multi-Purpose Synthetic Grease</strong> is an essential “spice” for electronics maintenance. I use it on any non-conductive moving parts. It’s a better option than lithium or graphite lubricants if you don’t need to work in extreme load or temperature conditions. However, it’s quite thick, so for more delicate appliances, you might want to consider something else.</p>

<h1 id="oil">Oil</h1>
<p>“Apply 2 or 3 drops of oil after every 2000 hours of operation,” according to the Technics Service Manual. The original SFWO 010 Technics oil is actually Anderol 465, a synthetic ISO 68 lubrication oil with SAE 30 viscosity. The only alternative I’ve found is <strong>3-in-one Motor Oil</strong>. Note that this is the special blue-bottle version designed for electric motors, not the regular 3-in-one multipurpose oil.</p>

<h1 id="fader-lubrication">Fader Lubrication</h1>
<p>DeoxIT F series offers a range of products specifically designed for conductive faders, and they work well for pitch fader renewal. However, it’s not always obvious which product to use unless you experiment with them. If you spray <strong>DeoxIT F5</strong> into the pitch fader, it will wash out any old grease (if present) and make the fader practically unusable. It should be paired with <strong>DeoxIT DFG-213</strong> fader grease, a thicker grease designed to smooth fader operation. So, if you’re confident enough to desolder the pitch fader, clean it with F5, and then lubricate it with DFG-213, you’ll achieve the best results. Otherwise, a few drops of <strong>DeoxIT F100L</strong> lubricant might help without disassembling the fader.</p>

<h1 id="after-soldering">After Soldering</h1>
<p><strong>Kontakt LR</strong> is my favorite technical spray. It magically gives a professional look to a PCB, making it appear as though it was factory-soldered. It removes flux and makes the PCB shine. I always add a touch of Kontakt LR after soldering. The smell, however, is horrible.</p>

<h1 id="voltage-regulator-montage">Voltage Regulator Montage</h1>
<p>Technics turntables have a voltage regulator connected to a heat sink with white, smelly thermal paste. After repainting the turntable or if the paste has dried out over time, it’s a good idea to apply a fresh layer. <strong>Arctic MX-4</strong> is a very popular option. While I can’t claim to be an expert in thermal pastes, this one is easy to apply, has no unpleasant smell, and, importantly, it doesn’t conduct electricity.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ilia Frolov</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Technics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Technical sprays, grease and oil for turntable service]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mysterious MN1400PA</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/mysterious-mn1400pa" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mysterious MN1400PA" /><published>2025-03-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/mysterious-mn1400pa</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/mysterious-mn1400pa"><![CDATA[<p>The MN1400PA is a 28-pin proprietary microcontroller developed by Technics, responsible for controlling the automatic functions of their turntables, including tonearm movement, start/stop and cueing mechanisms.</p>

<div class="blogPostImage">
<img src="/assets/posts/mysterious-mn1400pa/mn1400pa.jpeg" alt="MN1400PA Microcontroller" />
<div class="blogPostImageTitle">MN1400PA Microcontroller</div>
</div>

<p>This post is focused on the Technics SL-10 model, but the MN1400PA microcontroller is also used in other models, such as the SL-1600MK2. I had to dive deep into the microcontroller’s pinout and conditional logic to troubleshoot the start/stop functions and tonearm operations. Unfortunately, the SL-10 service manual doesn’t provide detailed information about the MN1400PA. I’m writing these notes as a cheatsheet for future myself and anyone else who might encounter similar issues—because, honestly, I just can’t keep all this in my head!</p>

<div class="blogPostImage">
<img src="/assets/posts/mysterious-mn1400pa/ports.png" alt="MN1400PA Microcontroller Ports" style="width: 200px" />
<div class="blogPostImageTitle">Microcontroller pins</div>
</div>

<p>Reference values are given with the S201 pushed, S401 pushed, Q403-5 covered with a tape. So that for the tonearm to start moving, pin 3 must be H, pin 11 - H, pin 12 - L and pin 21 - grounded.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">Pin</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Port</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Value</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Description</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">1</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Vss</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">0</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Ground</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">2</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">C09</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">H - enabled, <br />L - disabled</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Connected to D475 “Repeat” LED <br /> <img src="/assets/posts/mysterious-mn1400pa/D475.jpeg" alt="D475 Reset LED" /></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>3</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>C08</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>H - started</strong>, <br />L - stopped</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Start/Stop switch. Connected to the S201 switch <br /> <img src="/assets/posts/mysterious-mn1400pa/S201.jpeg" alt="S201 Switch" /></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">4</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">C07</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">H - started, <br />L - stopped</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Connected to the Base of Q407 (stylus illuminator)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">5</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">C06</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left">When connected to pin 9 - Cueing, to pin 10 - Repeat</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">6</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">C05</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left">When connected to pin 9 - Start, to pin 10 - Stop</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">7</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">A13</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">L when true, H otherwise</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Tonearm is in the leftmost position (end of a record), S403 switch is On. <br /> <img src="/assets/posts/mysterious-mn1400pa/S402_S403.jpeg" alt="S403 and S402 Switches" /></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">8</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">A12</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">L when true, H otherwise</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Tonearm is in the rightmost position (beginning of a record), S402 switch is On. See image for A13 port.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">9</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">A11</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Input from pins 5 and 6</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">10</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">A10</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Input from pins 5 and 6</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>11</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>B13</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>H</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Should be constantly H to indicate that the platter is spinning. Make sure that the mainboard is correctly assembled and the platter doesn’t touch anything while rotating.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>12</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>B12</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>L</strong> for 17cm record.</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Size detection, H for 17cm records. At least this Port must be H for the tonearm to start moving. Connected to the Q403 photo transistor. You may cover it with an electrical tape for troubleshooting while the top part of the turntable is open. <br /> <img src="/assets/posts/mysterious-mn1400pa/Q403_Q404_Q405.jpeg" alt="Q403, Q404 and Q405 Photo Transistors" /></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">13</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">B11</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">L for 25cm record.</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Size detection, H for 25cm records. Input from Q404, see B12 image.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">14</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">B10</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">L for 30cm record.</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Size detection, H for 30cm records. Input from Q405, see B12 image.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">15</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">E00</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Tonearm motor drive output signals</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">16</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">E01</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Tonearm motor drive output signals</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">17</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">E02</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Tonearm motor drive output signals</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">18</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">E03</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Tonearm motor drive output signals</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">19</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">-</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">20</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">RESET</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">H</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">When L, then the MCU state is reset</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>21</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>SNS0</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Ground</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Connected to the ground via S401 switch, that controls that the top part of the turntable is closed. You may solder top left and middle left pins of the S401 to have it always on for troubleshooting. <br /> <img src="/assets/posts/mysterious-mn1400pa/S401.jpeg" alt="S401 Switch" /></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">22</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">SNS1</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Impuls from a PC401 photo sensor, when the tonearm motor is rotating. <br /> <img src="/assets/posts/mysterious-mn1400pa/PC401.jpeg" alt="PC401" /></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">23</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">-</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">24</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">-</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">25</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">D02</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Goes to S202 speed selector switch</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">26</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">-</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">27</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Vdd</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">5V</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Power input</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">28</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">OSC</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"> </td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Clock signal</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>]]></content><author><name>Ilia Frolov</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Technics" /><category term="Repair" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Microcontroller that drives Technics turntable automatics]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Technics SL10 Blows 800mA Fuse</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/technics-sl10-blows-800ma-fuse" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technics SL10 Blows 800mA Fuse" /><published>2025-03-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/technics-sl10-blows-800ma-fuse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/technics-sl10-blows-800ma-fuse"><![CDATA[<p>I recently bought an SL10 in seemingly mint condition from Kleinanzeigen. I received the package, opened it, and eagerly connected the turntable, excited to hear the original Technics MC cartridge. I turned it on and quickly went to grab a vinyl record. But when I returned, the turntable was dead—no buttons were working, and no lights were flashing. What a disappointment.</p>

<div class="blogPostImage">
<img src="/assets/posts/technics-sl10-blows-800ma-fuse/sl10.jpg" alt="Technics SL10" />
<div class="blogPostImageTitle">Technics SL10 linear tracking turntable</div>
</div>

<p>The deck was consistently blowing the F2 800mA fuse within approximately 3 seconds of powering on (it’s a Träge fuse). It wasn’t an immediate blow, like when something is shorted.</p>

<div class="blogPostImage">
<img src="/assets/posts/technics-sl10-blows-800ma-fuse/fuse.jpg" alt="F2 800mA Fuse" />
<div class="blogPostImageTitle">F2 800mA fuse</div>
</div>

<p>I checked the power supply, main board, MC amplifier, and control board—no signs of a short or faulty components. I then hooked up my lab power supply and discovered that it was drawing around 1300mA. By the way, the SL10 can also be powered by an external 12V 800mA DC adapter, so 1300mA is quite unexpected and explains why the F2 fuse can’t handle this load.</p>

<p>The answer to the issue was fairly simple. The deck is trying to move the tonearm to its rightmost position when powered on. The tonearm is moved by a small electric motor, which appeared to be rusted or just stuck after years of inactivity. The motor, identified as KCN-22AS4A (4V), was drawing excess current in this rusted state—well above the designed limit.</p>

<div class="blogPostImage">
<img src="/assets/posts/technics-sl10-blows-800ma-fuse/motor.jpg" alt="Tonearm Motor" />
<div class="blogPostImageTitle">Tonearm motor</div>
</div>

<p>After cleaning it up and lubricating it with SAE 20 motor oil, the SL10 now draws around 800mA. I hope this small tip proves useful and saves time for others. I searched through many similar questions online but didn’t come across an answer like this.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ilia Frolov</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Technics" /><category term="Repair" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Investigating high current draw problem]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Technics SL1210 Height Adjustment Ring</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/technics-height-adjustment-ring" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technics SL1210 Height Adjustment Ring" /><published>2025-03-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/technics-height-adjustment-ring</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/technics-height-adjustment-ring"><![CDATA[<p>With the properly working height adjustment ring you could perfectly align your tonearm in parallel with a record.</p>

<div class="blogPostImage">
<img src="/assets/posts/technics-height-adjustment-ring/tonearm_parallel.png" alt="Technics Tonearm parallel to the record" />
<div class="blogPostImageTitle">Tonearm parallel to the record (taken from Panasonic website)</div>
</div>

<p>Probably the most common problem I’ve encountered with nearly every SL1200/1210 turntable is that the ring was stuck. The cause is quite simple—old grease becomes stiff over time, and the fine threading on the height adjustment ring no longer screws properly. Here’s my video attempt to capture the full process of maintaining the tonearm.</p>

<div class="embedded-video">
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xpd4BmoOFWs?si=OEYZD-2_98zZ4_IS" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Ilia Frolov</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Technics" /><category term="Repair" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The most common problem on Technics turntables]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s Phono Phönix?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/what-is-phono-phoenix" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s Phono Phönix?" /><published>2025-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/what-is-phono-phoenix</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/what-is-phono-phoenix"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been DJing, collecting vinyl, and owning a pair of Technics SL 1210 MK2 turntables since 2010, all while being an electronics enthusiast. In my personal restoration projects, I document and share the process of working on audio electronics repair through this blog, providing useful details along the way.</p>

<p>In the shop I offer high-quality 3D-printed spare parts, upgrades and accessories for DJ and Hi-Fi electronic devices. 
Using professional 3D printing equipment and the best engineering filaments.</p>

<p><b>Please note, that repair services are not offered at this moment.</b></p>]]></content><author><name>Ilia Frolov</name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Herzlich willkommen!]]></summary></entry></feed>